[Music]
stanford University
okay let's uh let's uh go
on in
fact let's let's forget for the moment
the spin system we'll come back to it
for sure um probably tonight in fact
definitely tonight but let's remind
ourselves of I think I wrote down four
principles of quantum mechanics last
time and I want to write them down
again and uh then uh move on to a fifth
principle in fact they're not all
independent
uh it's easier for me to explain them
one at a time than to try to derive from
the minimal absolute minimal number of
them and I don't think there's any
particular advantage in doing that so um
so we'll just write down all the
principles that I wrote down the first
one is that observables observables are
the things that you measure they could
be called measurables and if I if I had
if it was up to me I would have called
them measurables but uh they were called
observables observables are represented
and I'll just use the equal sign to
indicate that observables are
represented by hermission operators i'll
use the symbol L for the moment for
hermission operator not all operators
not all linear operators are hermission
and it will not always be the case that
the symbol L will stand for a hermission
operator but right now L stands for a
hermission operator any hermission
operator every observable is identified
with a hermission operator now the
question of whether every hermission
operator is a thing which can be
measured is a generally hard question
and you have to you know what can and
can't be measured depends on what kind
of materials you have available all
kinds of
things generally the um the abstract
rule that uh that or the folk rule let's
call it is that any hermission operator
is identified with an observable and
someday somebody will figure out how to
measure it okay but uh the other way
that any observable is identified with a
hermission operator that's for sure um
the igen values of a hermission operator
let's call them
lambdas lambda is the igen value of l
the igen values represent the possible
numerical values that l can exhibit when
it's measured okay so I en
values
values of
L which equal
lambda
no they
represent the
possible observed or the possible
outcome of experiment possible
outcome of an experiment to measure
L of L
measurement okay I think we had a third
one along the line here yeah physically
distinguishable states now let's let's
just see what physically distingu
distinguishable states mean
um certainly up and down are physically
distinguishable and the meaning of
saying two states are physically
distinguishable is that there exists a
measurement of some kind that you can do
that can tell you the difference between
an upstate and a down state in other
words somebody hands you a spin from out
of their pocket and they say "I created
this
spin i prepared it in a state which is
either up or down can you do an
experiment to unambiguously tell me
which one it is?" Yes you tilt your
apparatus until it's pointing along the
z-axis and you make the measurement if
the state was up you will get plus one
if the state is down you will get minus
one no
ambiguity the same is true for left and
right different measurement different
thing that you would measure you would
measure the x component and you would
tilt your apparatus along the
x-axis but same uh same deal on the
other hand supposing somebody that same
person came along and said "Here I'm
going to give you a spin here it is and
that spin I either
prepared up or I prepared it
right i am not going to tell you which
way I prepared it i'm not going to tell
you which way I tilted my apparatus when
I did the experime when I did the
preparation i'm just going to tell you
it's either left sorry it's either up or
right can you do a experiment which will
uniquely tell you the difference the
answer is no for example supposing you
decide to measure the spin along the
z-axis well if it's up you'll get plus
one if it's right with 50% probability
you'll get plus one so you can't be sure
whether you uh whether you
uh whether you were up or right
what do you get if you oriented at 45°
still you would have a
probability for yeah yeah
yeah uh it would not be unambiguous
right okay so the next postulate excuse
me in your last statement that's
assuming that it was prepared along the
z-axis if it had been prepared along the
x- axis
then
it if you if you measured the x- axis
first you that difference the if you
measure the x- axis first you'll find
something
out but uh you could have found out
exactly the same answer if it was along
the z axis in either case there is some
probability of getting the same
answer whether it was up or right
there's no experiment you can do which
unambiguously will uh will
determine which it was all right so that
leads to the notion I'm not going to try
to give a a more precise uh definition
of it that leads to the notion of
physically distinguishable states by
which is meant that there exists an
experiment or a set of experiments that
can unambiguously determine which of the
two states you're talking about the next
postulate is that physically distinct or
physically distinguishable states are
represented by orthogonal
vectors okay okay so physically
distinct distinct distinguishable same
thing little easier to write distinct
physically distinct
states
imply
orthogonality all right I said that
observables are hermission
operators i could have just said linear
operators let's leave it at linear
operators for the
moment but let's add a postulate that
the result of every experiment every
simple primitive experiment is a real
number if it's a real number if it's a
complex number it really means that two
things two independent things were
measured the actual results that come
out of your apparatus that come out of
your um uh you know well the needles on
your apparatus they're real numbers so
I'll add that as a postulate the results
of experiments are always real numbers
and therefore the iigen values of
observables are real numbers now that
does not prove that the operator is a
hermission not enough not enough the
other added thing is that the various
igen vectors with different igen values
physic physically distinguishable states
are orthogonal okay that's this third
postulate and that tells you that
observables are hermission
operators it's the hermission
operators whose igen values are always
real and
whose en vectors are orthogonal that's
necessary and sufficient uh
so this one as I said they're not all
completely uh independent of each
other
[Music]
one two three and let's write number
four
now i forgot what four is oh
well uh
um yeah what was for
Yeah
ah the probability the probability
principle okay the probability principle
it's al it's also called Bourne's
rule max Bourne Bourne's rule let's just
call it Bourne bourne rule but it's a
rule for probabilities so far none of
this has much content the added content
well no it has content but the real bite
here is
uh for the prediction of
probabilities for various experiments
and the Bourne rule is the rule for how
to calculate probabilities
the Borne rule says if you if your
system has been prepared in state
A all right
system in A and you
measure
L the observable L now I'm using
interchangeably the physical idea of the
observable with the operator which
represents it i'm not going to make a
special language where the operator will
always be called the operator and the
observable with L same they they they
come in pairs all right so if you if the
system has been prepared in state A and
you measure L you measure L the outcome
is going to be one of the igen values so
the only question you can ask is what is
the probability that you get the answer
lambda okay one of one of the specific
values the answer
is the
probability the probability that you get
result lambda
that's the probability that you get out
of the various igen values that you get
lambda is
equal to the square of the inner
product of the state
vector that the system was in with the
igen vector corresponding the normalized
igen vector all vectors are normalized
now
uh the inner product of a with lambda
squared a with lambda the inner product
sometimes incidentally the the inner
product is called the overlap it's a
measure if we said that orthogonal
orthogonality is complete
distinguishability uh unique and uh
complete
distinguishability then a lack of
orthogonality
represents to some extent the the the
inability to make the clear distinction
between two states yeah all right so
this is this is yeah question if well I
I'm surprised to see lambda represented
as a vector because it's a value no no
all right the notation
is every value is associated with an
igen vector
i'll just write E vector and the
notation is that the vector labeled by
lambda is the igen vector associated
with the igen value lambda that's a good
point i mean that you know
um the problem with trying to be a
purist about notations is that notations
get very complicated and they get so
complicated that they're difficult to
read there are too many uh indices
there's too many different letters you
have to use so yeah sometimes we use a
slightly excuse the word bastardized
notation
uh where uh where we
conflate a symbol for a vector with a
symbol in this case for an igen value
uh good okay uh yes that's the
probability principle or B's
rule and let's just look at it for a
minute you might ask why the square why
the square of the absolute value well in
general these overlaps are neither
positive not even real in general
overlaps between two vectors are not
necessarily real in fact in general
they're not they're comp we're talking
about a complex vector
space and if the components of the
vectors are complex and generally inner
product will not even be real let
alone positive okay on the other hand
the square of the uh or the absolute
value of the square the square of the
absolute value of the inner product that
is real it's not only real it's also
positive okay so this has a chance to be
a candidate for probability whereas the
inner product itself doesn't the inner
product itself is called a probability
amplitude so a probability amplitude is
a thing that you square in in the sense
of absolute value to compute a
probability
needless to say the
um the justification for these
principles in the end is experiment on
the other hand you could ask how much
can I bend them and still make physical
sense out of the predictions the answer
is nobody has ever found a way to change
the rules of quantum mechanics and still
preserve um a reasonable reasonably
logical structure so you'll eventually
get familiar with these principles yeah
which of these uh principles took you
from several possible outcomes to one
actual outcome well okay if A is an igen
vector of L of L if it is if the if the
state starting state of the system
happens to be an igen vector of L then
it will only have an inner product with
one of the igen vectors right so that's
again these are good questions say if
you say L cat lambda equals lambda cat
lambda it kind of shows
yeah that's right excuse me is
it what if lambda is an value for
multiple vectors all yeah still the rule
is is the same
uh but what you right okay I'll give you
two answers the first answer is
Don't worry about the case where the
igen values may be the same because it's
very special but that's not good enough
let me uh let me let me say what the
right answer is the right answer is if
if you want the probability for a given
value of lambda and there's more than
one igen vector with the same value of
lambda then you add them you simply add
the sums of the squares of the uh just
probability addition um so the questions
tonight are really good uh yeah and what
about the case where a has overlap of
several different Yeah yeah then you
then you then you take the sums of the
squares of
them you take the sums of the square if
there are several different vectors all
with the same igen value first of all
you make them perpendicular to each
other you can always make them
perpendicular to each other different
values no no even if they're the same
igen value uh there's the theorem okay
let's go back to the theorem the theorem
says that the igen vectors with
different igen values are
orthogonal it doesn't tell you anything
about the igen vectors for the same igen
value all right so supposing you have
two igen vectors with the same igen
value then it's also true that any
linear combination of those two igen
vectors is also an igen vector with the
same igen value for example let's
suppose
lambda lambda 1 and lambda 2 now these
are not two different values of lambda
these are the same value of lambda but
two different igen vectors maybe we
should write it like this lambda 1 and
lambda 2 two different igen vectors both
exhibiting the same igen value
then you can take any what what that
means is that L on lambda 1 equals
lambda * lambda
1 L on lambda 2 equals lambda lambda
2 multiply this by any complex number
alpha this one by any complex number
beta and add the two equations
what you find is that L on the linear
combination the linear sum alpha lambda
1 plus beta lambda
2 is equal on this side now you have
lambda times the same thing as in the
bracket here in other words if you have
two igen vectors with the same igen
value you can add them with arbitrary
coefficients and they remain igen
vectors now given two distinct
vectors given two distinct vectors and
all the possible linear combinations of
them you can always find perpendicular
combinations you got this one you got
this one now we can always add them or
subtract them with coefficients to make
them perpendicular
so the rest of the theorem
is that if the two igen values are the
same you have the freedom to choose two
vectors which are
perpendicular which are orthogonal all
right in the end of the day to summarize
a theorem is that um given a hermission
operator its igen vectors can be chosen
so that uh so that they form a basis so
that they're
orthonormal perpendicular to each other
and
normalized okay so where were we
um that was an interruption but I don't
remember where I was that's the problem
with interruptions
um we just finished Bourne's rule h you
were just talking about Bourne's rule
yes I was talking about Bourne's rule
right oh good okay so now if you happen
to have several Igen vectors let's say
lambda 1 and lambda 2 both with the same
value then you construct the overlap of
the state vector with lambda 1 you
construct the
overlap of the same of the state vector
with lambda 2 you square this one you
square this one and you add them in
other words you simply add the
probabilities
uh for the two possible ways that you
could get the same uh lambda just the
sum of probabilities thank you
Sanjay you're already too late i already
got
Oreos but uh my wife would
say this is probably healthier than
Oreos yeah it is
what
yeah eat the Oreos
excuse me
okay
yeah go ahead
loud and clear could we say um also that
the reason why those things are squared
regardless of whether they're complex or
not is so that the total probability
adds to one right yes mhm
right we know it's the sums of the
squares of these things which add up to
one for normalized states for normalized
vectors that's right
i'm not sure
which which one implies which but
clearly they fit together very nicely
good okay
question is it possible to get an
unambiguous result from an unprepared
experiment
i'm not sure what an unprepared
experiment means but I think I think
what you're asking is supposing somebody
gives you a spin and they don't tell you
anything about how they prepared it they
just say "Here it is i give it to you i
tell you
nothing then it is not possible to find
an experiment which has an unambiguous
answer
another good
point okay
now now we need to
come to a new idea and a new question
in classical
mechanics all of this this whole story
here was summarized
uh when I uh showed you a heads and a
tail and I said those are the two
possible states of a simple system i
didn't we didn't talk about measuring it
you know it was all sort of obvious and
we didn't have to uh because we know
that measuring is doesn't do very much
to a system you measure but you uh that
doesn't change the system in any way
here we come to a much more complicated
story but the story up till now is
really the quantum mechanical analog of
just specifying that you have a
collection of
states the next question we asked was
how do states change with
time that we called in the classical
case dynamical laws of motion or
dynamical laws of nature or whatever the
rule for how a state changes
if you remember there were some examples
uh the coin a simple example would be
put the coin down and the rule is
nothing happens it just stays the same
way well that's pretty trivial another
possible law is in each interval of time
and we have a a strooscopic time that we
can imagine and in each interval of time
it flips up heads tails heads tails
heads tails that's a perfectly good law
uh we talked about the concept the same
concept in the context of a die with six
faces or any number of faces including
continuous infinity same basic idea the
laws of physics are an updating from
instant to instant of a configuration
they tell you how the configuration
changes and if you have good laws in
classical physics they're
deterministic they tell you how the
state changes but also another rule and
the other rule we called
reversibility reversibility was
basically just the idea that states
don't run into each other that states
which are
distinguishable namely different heads
and tails are
distinguishable are two states which are
different will evolve mathematically and
stay
different all right that was the idea of
reversibility and what it comes down to
is exactly that that if you know the
state at any instant you not only will
know what comes next but you will also
know what came before because there's no
uh chance that states run together
uh and uh two different states giving
you the same
outcome then you wouldn't be able to
tell where you came from so
reversibility is the idea we also called
it information conservation and I
suspect I referred to it as the minus
first law minus first because it comes
before everything
else quantum mechanics also has a rule
of both reversibility and information
conservation you can call it the minus
first
law uh but it comes down to the same
thing states which are distinguishable
in the sense that I said that there
exists an experiment that uniquely
distinguishes them stay
uh
distinguishable all right so now we want
to talk about how states evolve with
time we're going to come
back and discuss this in the context of
the spin it's the simplest system of
quantum mechanics and it's a good idea
to get it all down for that but let's
talk about it uh more
generally okay here is the
postulate the postulate is that if you
have the if you have a system at time at
some specific time let's call it at time
zero and I'm going to start changing my
notation for states instead of calling
them a and b I'm going to start using a
uh a notation which is more or less a
standard notation in quantum mechanics
call them
pai pi is a Greek letter and psi is a
commonly used letter to represent the
state of a system now the states of
systems do change with time so you have
to think of these these vectors as being
functions of time they evolve so let's
put that in here in the following way s
of S of T this simply represents a state
which changes with
time which state could be any
state it's not the same after a certain
time as it was to begin with but we're
following one specific state of a system
that's been prepared and then allowed to
evolve by whatever means things
evolve all right the postulate is that s
of
t can be
obtained from s of
zero this means time zero by an
operation on s of zero a unique definite
operation which is governed by the laws
by the quantum mechanical laws for that
system
so we have to do something to the vector
doesn't doesn't stay the same so let's
represent what we do by the operation of
some kind of
operator now incidentally we didn't have
to start with time uh zero we could have
started with time uh something else and
evolved by amount t so this t here
really represents the time of evolution
from the initial state to the final
state or not necessarily final but the
state at some
time the basic postulate two basic
postulates the first is that u is a
linear operator that U is a linear
operator and the same
U for any state whatever the initial
state
is you put that here and you hit it with
the same U the same operator in other
words there is a this is called the time
development operator it's a linear
operator
uh and it evolves a state from one
instant to
another you could try to ask what would
happen if you made a
more general
hypothesis for example you might have
the hypothesis that U depends on the
initial state or you might have the
hypothesis that U is an operation but
not a linear operator some other kind of
operation you can try it you'll very
shortly run into big troubles with all
kinds of things it's been tried i
guarantee you it's been tried and
repeatedly every so often some physicist
will uh try to invent something and then
some other person will come along and
say "Look that has troubles with
locality or it has troubles with
causality or it has troubles with
probability
interpretation." And uh you're free to
try i've given up
trying i I actually never
tried
uh right okay so u is a linear
operator with all the rules for linear
operators but one other thing and that's
this idea of conservation of information
or conservation of
distinguishability that if you have two
states two different states of the same
system and you evolve them let's call
phi of
t fi capital
phi that's given by the same u of t the
same operator times phi at time zero
Then if
fi to begin with is orthogonal to
sigh in other words if they're
physically distinguishable to begin with
then they will remain orthogonal for all
time
is there anything to the fact that she
used uppercase letters on the left and
lower case again the Greek letters are
uppercase on the left and lower case on
the right is that just
I guess I'm
sloppy no right all right so
orthogonality breeds
orthogonality physically distinct states
evolve to physically distinct
states uh
distinguishability remains intact it's
the immediate analog of the minus first
law of classical
mechanics so let's see if we can find
out what it says oh
incidentally it's very easy to prove
from that well what does it say it says
that if s and fi were initially
orthogonal I'm all right
no if they're initially orthogonal
if
then don't ask me to make capital
letters it's it's much quicker to make
the lowercase ones but
uh I mean capital here i mean uppercase
then this is true and it remains true
for all time it's an easy exercise i
will leave it to you to prove that if
orthogonality is preserved that you can
say a stronger thing it's implied by
this you can say if you take any two
vectors which may or may not be
orthogonal the inner product between
them stays constant with time there's a
nice little trick you take any two
vectors you expand them in basis vectors
and then you assume that the basis
vectors remain orthogonal with time then
you can prove that the inner products of
any two vectors is time
independent so it follows from the
orthogonality the um the evolution of
orthogonality that the inner product
between two states remains the same the
overlap between them remains the same
there's a sense in which the overlap
between two states is a is of course a
measure of their similarity and what it
says is the degree of similarity remains
the
same okay let's see if we can figure out
what that means for you
what it says let's let's rewrite this by
plugging in for phi of t and s of t the
product u * phi and u * s but before we
do we have to remember that we have to
flip this equation
whoops chocolate
par is this chocolate yeah it is
chocolate
we have to flip it from a cat vector to
a bra vector equation okay so let's do
so this is s of
t
equals s of
0 not times u but times what
u dagger the hermission
conjugate not the compass it's related
to the complex conjugate but the
hermission conjugate all right so now we
plug this into this equation here and
what it says let's write it
out do a little bit of
eraser for arbitraries they don't have
to be orthogonal whatever they are they
have some inner product that's equal to
s of zero
u dagger of
t u of
t five of
zero all I've done is plug in for phi u
of t for s u dagger of t now the product
ud dagger times u is another operator
what is the product of two operators we
didn't talk about this but the product
of two operators is a very simple
concept uh you take a linear operator
and you apply it to a vector and then
you take the result and you apply
another operator to it the process of
repeatedly applying two operators gives
you an operation which is called the
product of the two operators so that's
what this is first you hit fi with U and
then you hit the result with your
dagger and what this says is that for
any fi and sigh any fi and sigh at
all that when you plug in here u dagger
and u the product of you dagger and u
you get
something which is exactly the same as
had you
not evolved the
state the inner product stays the same
whoops I think I made a mistake one of
these should be five
right all right so that's the principle
of conservation of overlap if you like
well here's a theorem I we don't need to
this is again very very easily proved by
going to a basis very easily proved that
if the matrix elements this is called
the matrix elements or the uh the
product like this if
um this equation is true for any pair of
vectors other words I I'll write the
I'll write the theorem in general if you
have an operator Let's call it K for U
dagger u and for any pair of vectors
s
ki is equal to
sci for any pair of vectors whatever it
follows that k is the unit operator the
unit operator is the operator which does
nothing just gives you back the same
vector
so it follows then that U dagger time U
must be the unit operator that's the
content of conservation
of
overlap u
dagger of T for any T time U of
T is equal to the unit
operator meaning the operator which does
nothing just gives you back the same
vector
question mhm can you then say that one
is the inverse of the other in matrix
algebra yes you can okay yes you can
indeed
right let's examine this a little bit
now in particular let's examine it for
very very small
time for very small
time in other words where you only
evolve the system by a tiny little
incremental time
let's call the incremental time epsilon
right let's write that u of epsilon now
first of all what is u of
zero no time evolution at
all just one just a unit operator so for
a very small epsilon
u must be itself close to the unit
operator plus a small deviation
presumably of order epsilon and that
will be right it will be of order
epsilon so there will be something of
order epsilon times another operator
here i'm going to make use of freedom
and
uh that I have and I'm going to
put a minus sign here we're going to put
an operator over here this minus sign
has no content yet unless I know what
the operator is over here the minus sign
it just absorbs into the definition and
I'm also going to put an I
here again there's no content
yet because I haven't told you anything
about H h is some operator
epsilon time H is just an operator and I
epsilon H is just an operator so I have
not really said anything other than for
small epsilon the operator U is close to
the identity how close of order epsilon
and then there may be additional things
of order epsilon squared epsilon cubed
but we're going to drop them and study
this equation oh I should we should name
we should give a name to this equation
here more specifically we should give a
name to operators which satisfy this
rule u dagger time U is equal to one or
as was said that U dagger the hermission
conjugate of U is the inverse of
U such operators are called unitary
u is a unitary operator so this is again
this is a restatement of the principle
of conservation of uh of
overlap all right let's now
apply this equation this condition to u
of epsilon and see what we find out
about
h okay so let's bring it over to this
blackboard u of epsilon is equal to 1 -
i epsilon h now let's do it over here
all right what about ud dagger ud dagger
is the hermission
conjugate the hermission conjugate of
one is just one but then we have to
complex conjugate plus i epsilon and
then we have to hermission conjugate
h
okay all right so here is ud dagger and
here is u and now let's multiply them
together and set the result equal to one
to order epsilon to order
epsilon okay so what do we have we have
u dagger is
1 + i epsilon * h
dagger time 1 - i epsilon
h that has to equal
1 and now just expand it out to order
epsilon 1 plus i
epsilon h dagger minus
h equals
1 as I said through that's to the
approximation that epsilon is so small
that it square can be completely ignored
compared to order
epsilon right so the ones
cancel and basically what we find is
that h dagger minus h has to be zero
this we we canceled out the ones we get
zero on the right hand side and so to
order epsilon
uh h has to equal h
dagger this is the
condition that H be
hermission okay now I didn't call it H
for hermission i called it H for
something else i called it H for
Hamiltonian okay what it has to do with
the Hamiltonian of classical mechanics
will eventually become clear right the
Hamiltonian for classical mechanics also
enters in to the equations for how
systems evolve from one instant to the
to to the next
but of course that's not a good enough
reason to call this the Hamiltonian we
want to see that it enters the equations
in a way very very similar to the way uh
the Hamiltonian enters into classical
mechanics and it does
uh it is also the thing
which it's hermission
right that
means that it's an observable or it
could be an
observable it's a hermission operator
it could be an observable and it isn't
observable it's the Hamiltonian it's the
energy hamiltonian and energy are the
same this is what the energy of a system
is it's the Hamiltonian which generates
the evolution of state vectors according
to this rule here yeah
it could be any hermission operator at
the moment
now what determines what hermission
operator you put there well it can't be
yes it can be any hermission operator
associated with the system you're
studying right uh if we're studying a
system of one spin we want to make it up
out of operators that are associated
with the spin uh so yes it can be any
operator but it's uh either experiment
or some this the same things which
govern why you choose one Hamiltonian or
loanian in classical mechanics either
experiment some prejudice about the way
things work some symmetry
principle whatever uh whatever you have
that might give you a clue as to what h
is at the end of the day you may have to
resort to experiment to find out but uh
But um whatever whatever it is okay so
uh
that's right so now let's let's rewrite
our equation let's rewrite question yeah
so when you do that expansion like that
normally then uh h is a constant that's
what you normally mean when you do that
first order expansion so it' be it's h
of h is an operator i mean it's a it's
not a function of time when in that case
right okay
not a function of epsilon
the situation with a possible explicit
time dependence of h is the same as in
classical
physics in classical physics h can
depend on time for example if you have a
particle moving in a magnetic field and
the strength of the magnets is being
varied with time by changing the current
through the electro
romagnet then the Hamiltonian for the
particle moving in a magnetic field is
time dependent okay otherwise if you
have the if the parameters of the
problem are not varying with time then
you say the Hamiltonian is not time it's
exactly the same exact
do you say h of zero yeah yeah no that
that's right that that's right in
principle h could be a function of time
let's take the case where it's not and
what that corresponds
to is the situation where the parameters
of the problem are not time
dependent where in classical physics we
called it time translation invariance
okay remember in classical physics uh
time translation invariance which means
like every time is the same as every
other time okay you do the experiment
the same experiment at a later time will
have the same output as the as the
identical experiment at an earlier time
the statement of that principle time
translation and variance is that H does
not have explicit dependence on time
it's just an operator which doesn't
depend on time as I said you can imagine
situations where you're ramping up the
current uh an electromagnet or the
universe is expanding or god knows what
there's some explicit time dependence
then h can be time uh time dependent now
do you remember what happens to energy
conservation if the Hamiltonian is time
dependent
down the drain right same thing here if
the Hamiltonian is time dependent and we
haven't yet seen why why there might be
a conservation of energy we'll come to
that but
um all right okay so let's come back
then to this equation over here question
what happens at the long time what
happens small for the small epsilon time
sorry what say it again this is for the
small infinite decimal small yes yeah
we'll come to that basically you just
multiply them
together all right we we'll come to that
okay
or you can think of it another way after
you've updated by a small amount of time
you just do it again and again and again
right uh you just do it
repeatedly but we can use this to derive
a differential equation for the way the
state changes with time let's do
that
um let's do
that okay so let's look at the state of
the system at a time
epsilon and this time epsilon could be
thought of as a time epsilon right after
some arbitrary time which I'm going to
call zero but it doesn't matter so I of
epsilon is equal to
1 - i h
epsilon minus i h epsilon
time s let's say at time
z or another way to say it is that s of
epsilon minus s of zero this is the
small incremental change in the state
vector
That's equal to minus I
epsilon operation by h on
s now as I said the this zero here
doesn't have to be zero it could be any
time as long as epsilon is epsilon units
after the starting time okay let's
divide this equation by epsilon
you're allowed to do this because you
can multiply vectors by numbers so we're
just multiplying both sides by 1 over
epsilon 1 over epsilon times this whole
thing okay what's this thing on the left
hand side 1 over epsilon times the
difference of two
things which are by which at two
slightly different times that's just the
time derivative of this
vector we haven't talked very much about
taking derivatives of vectors but it's
clear you can do that you can take the
difference between two vectors that's
perfectly well defined uh they will be
close to each other if epsilon is small
if you divide by the small epsilon
you'll get something which on the right
hand side is
just the time
derivative of
s the time derivative of s
equals minus i
h s at any given time it doesn't as I
said it doesn't have to be at time zero
at any given time if you want to find
out how the state of the system changes
over an incremental time interval this
is
your this is your
equation completely analogous to the way
you update classical systems
but
because because knowing the state vector
is not the same as knowing the values of
the
uh experimental outputs of experiments
you can know the state and still there
can be ambiguity or uncertainty in the
value of an experiment this tells you
how states change but it doesn't tell
you how the results of experiment change
the experiment results of experiments
are still statistical but with a
continuously updated state
vector okay this is this equation has a
name of this equation is the generalized
time dependent Schroinger equation this
is the general form this is the
Schroinger equation specific versions
what Schroinger wrote down was a very
specific version of this we're going to
come to that later in in a course but
this is the general
idea the rate of all right I don't need
to say it again this is what it is but
of course in order to use it you have to
know what h is
question so all of this is dependent on
the reversibility of the system is that
right yes so I guess or the conservation
of inner product right so I guess
stepping back how does that match the
fact that if you take an up vector and a
down vector and you measure them along
the horizontal axis they sort of both
end up you know in sort of I guess to be
inable states that's a good question
you have to remember when you do that
you're intervening with an
apparatus in order to follow the system
under those circumstances you have to
include the apparatus as part of the
system you cannot interact with the
system and not include the things which
are interacting with it in the system
classically it's not such a bad uh sin
but quantum mechanically if something
interacts with a system strongly enough
to to affect it well strongly enough to
measure it you have to include it as
part of the system now this is the way a
system evolves if it's isolated and
completely not in contact with anything
else we will have to come back to ask
how it evolves what happens when you put
it in contact with a measuring apparatus
we'll have to have a model for how
measurements take place but this is the
way the system behaves if nobody
disturbs it during the course of the
evolution from time zero to time
t okay we'll have to come back to that
it's an important question
oh
boy yeah really just two assumptions
well maybe three first is that time
evolution takes place by a linear
operator called U and that operator is
independent of a state that it's acting
on okay with me okay uh that's the first
statement the next statement is that
inner products are conserved with time
and that tells you that U is
unitary
okay from
that we went over to here and discovered
that for the small little incremental
change is governed by a hermission
operator
okay so we get to the idea of a
Hamiltonian
and then we just rewrote that and said
look the small little incremental change
could be thought of as 1 over epsilon
times the time derivative of the state
vector okay so this this is uh this is
the Schroinger
equation how do you uh solve the problem
if there's a long time interval not a
short time interval you basically solve
this equation and we'll talk about how
you solve this equation we'll do so for
lots of examples but
um
okay to go
on and explain what this has to do with
classical mechanics or what it has to do
with the corresponding concepts in
classical mechanics we need a couple of
ideas
uh about how you
relate classical ideas to quantum
mechanical ideas we need the idea of
what is called the expectation value of
an
observable it's a bad
name it's a bad name because the
expectation value as defined may have
very little to do with what you expect
the experiment to give
uh this doesn't have much to do with
quantum mechanics it's just an issue of
probability theory i think we've talked
about this before but I'll just remind
you if you have a probability
distribution which looks like
this then the least likely answer that
you could possibly get is right over
here it's also the expectation value so
it's it's a poor a poorly chosen
terminology
the right terminology should sometimes
some uh
some fancy people I won't name Murray
Galman but
uh some fancy people like to call it the
expected value well it's even less the
expected value than it is the
expectation value it's the average value
it's the average value and the average
value of something can be a value which
the thing can't even take on the
possible value that it couldn't even
have the average value for example if
you assign assign heads plus one and
tails minus one and you flip the coin
what's the average zero but you can't
get zero so it's got nothing to do with
the expected value of an
experiment uh but nevertheless it's
called the expectation value and we will
we will call it the expectation value
but it's the average value let's talk
about the average value of a
observable given a particular state
all right so our state is
a I said I was going to change the sigh
but sometimes I will sometimes I won't
could we go back to the expectation
value
maybe I I think I just have to clear my
head of statistics but when I look at
that picture you draw I a frequency
distribution
so to me it's the middle is not the
average it really is the expected value
it's the value that's going to occur
most frequently no no definitely not
this one here it never occurs never ever
ever let's even make it worse okay what
are the X and Y values what do the X and
Y axis represent i keep saying P is the
probability x is some variable something
that you measure
this could be the probability for
finding a particle at different
locations
okay all
right it could be that for some
particular state the probability let's
let's make it symmetric about the origin
just
to it could be that the probability
distribution looks like
this i mean I meant to make this
symmetric and is really very very zero
in a neighborhood of the origin
here there's no sense in which x equals
0 is expected you can do the experiment
forever and ever and ever and you will
never get x equals
z you'll either get an x somewhere in
here or here so to call it the expect
the expected or the expectation value is
sort of a
misnomer it is the average value
defining averages in a very particular
way now uh for many many smooth
probability distributions in particular
probability distributions that don't
have big holes in them something like
this let's say it can very often be the
case and very often is the case that the
uh that the probabil that the um that
the average value is the most likely
value to get so it's it's this they call
it the mode the most likely value what's
the peak the peak there is the most
likely value
uh yes by definition the top of the peak
is and in many many cases if you have
nice simple probability Gaussian
probability you know bell-shaped curves
and so forth then the expectation value
or the average value is usually quite
close to the a average and uh peak value
and so forth they're all usually close
to each other but certainly there can be
violent uh exceptions the coin or the
spin which can only be plus one and
minus one and never
zero the expectation value and the
average value are quite different okay
but that that's just a little sermon and
gave me a chance to badmouth my friend
Marie Galman
question if you take a a spin where the
apparatus is
perpendicular then the probability is
50% but you make it very unlucky you hit
a million ups in a row the average would
be up but that's not accurate yeah
well okay it depends on what you mean by
average there's a notion of average
which is strictly mathematical and we're
going to write it down in a minute
uh there is
a
unwritten law which I think it's safe to
say nobody really
understands but uh it's the law of large
numbers that if you do a thing enough
times how many
times I don't know if you do a thing
enough times you do an experiment enough
times
uh the average gotten by averaging The
results of your experiment will be equal
to the average defined mathematically to
within what to within the margin of
error what is a margin of
error there's a specific number does it
really mean that every time you do it
the answer will come out within the
margin of error no all right so we're
assuming standard probability theory
that if you do a a thing enough plus
this extra little ingredient this extra
physical assumption I don't know I don't
even know what to call it that if you
repeat an experiment enough times the
average of your data will be the
mathematical average can anybody prove
that no
that's a uh that's a law of large
numbers theorem or something like that
no no no no there's nothing you can do
to prove it the reason you can't prove
it is because sooner or later
somewhere's in the multiverse
somewhere's there's going to be an
exception to it no matter how many times
if you do it a zillion times a zillion
is a number incidentally it's not it's
not infinity a zillion is one with a
logarithm of a zillion zeros after it or
something like that i don't know
uh right if you do an experiment if
you and uh and there's enough
repetitions of it eventually somewhere
someplace there's going to be a
violation of it this is closely
connected to um to the second law of
thermodynamics you know there was a
principle the second law of
thermodynamics says that the entropy
never
decreases boltzman was never able to
prove that and he finally realized that
the right law is the entropy probably
never decreases except when it does
which is rarely except when it
does so I am not going to try to give
you an explanation of why probability
theory works this is to me very puzzling
but uh we will assume probability theory
works the statement that it works is the
same as the statement that the average
of your data will be for a big enough
experiment will be the mathematical
average all right so let's talk well
let's come over to the side here first
and just say supposing we have a
collection of uh uh we have a
probability distribution for some
variable let's say for lambda lambda one
of the igen value going to measure an
igen value of l suppos supposeding we
have a probability for lambda there it
is right there the thing I called prob
of lambda
uh probability for
lambda and lambda can take on a whole
bunch of different values
lambda subi let's call them so this
becomes the probability for lambda sub i
then the average the definition of the
average is the sum over
i of lambda i times the probability for
lambda i that's the definition of the
average and we'll represent the average
by the
symbol the bracket symbol well why it's
labeled by the bracket symbol we'll come
to okay but that's the definition
standard probability theory definition
of the average of a quantity the
quantity times the probability that the
quantity takes on that particular value
summed over I and as I said that's
standard definition of average
okay uh what is the average in a state a
of the observable lambda so let's say
that a is
expanded in a basis which
basis the basis of igen vectors of l of
of uh of l right remember l is a
hermission operator it's igen vectors
form a basis you can expand vectors in
an orthonormal basis so let's write this
in the form alpha subi sum over i lambda
subi remember that the lambdas are an
orthonormal
basis what is the
probability lambda in the state I
probability for lambda I is equal to
alpha* i alpha
i
right I maintain oh this is the
probability and the average of lambda
let's call the average of lambda is the
sum over i lambda sub i alpha i* alpha
i all I've done is plug
In let me prove that this is the same
thing as taking the vector A the bra
vector A and sandwiching between the bra
vector A and the K vector A the operator
L the operator L is the operator whose
igen values are
lambda let's see if we can prove that
it's actually quite easy all we do is
say let's just plug in let's come to
another blackboard plug in and
uh and see if we can prove
that all right so let's calculate
this creature over here
a is this summation and let's use also
that the bra vector A is the summation
over I of lambda sub I alpha*
I all right so we make a sandwich the
sandwich is the sum over I and J why
there are two sums one for the bra cat
one for the bra and one for the
cat lambda
subj alpha*
j this is the bra vector a and then we
put l there and then we put the k vector
alpha i lambda
i just pure
pluginology now what is l when it acts
on lambda subi
lambda subs are the igen vectors of
L so when L acts on lambda subi we still
have some I J lambda
J alpha* J alpha I and now L hits lambda
I and it gives us lambda
subi times lambda I now all this junk in
here is just a number for each I and J
for each I and J this is just a
number so that means we are called upon
to take the inner product of lambda I
with lambda J what is that
right it's one or zero depending on
whether I equals J or not given
that this sum the double sum collapses
to a single sum in which lambda I and
lambda J are identified and this just
becomes sum on
I lambda I well
okay let's uh cut uh let's cut through
some of the
steps if if J is not equal to I you get
nothing if J is equal to I the inner
product is just one so this just becomes
the sum over I alpha* I alpha I lambda
I which is
exactly what we have over here
so we've proved this relationship here
that the
average of any observable is just the
sandwich the bracket the bracket the
bracket the bracket the bracket made out
of
sandwiching L the observable between a
bracket between a bra and a cat okay
that's the the same bron ket the bronet
associated with the state of the
Right that's where this notation of uh
bracket bracket comes from okay that's a
good thing to know that if you want the
average of a quantity just sandwich it
between the bracket the bracket
representing the
state any questions about that
okay now I'm going to tell you what
we're going to do what we're going to do
is we're going to try to find
equations governing the time evolution
of these average values
the idea is that under suitable
reasonable circumstances if the
probability distributions are nicely
shaped if they have a sort of nice
bell-shaped curve that um that by
calculating the time evolution of
averages you're doing something pretty
close to what classical physics uh would
instruct you to do about calculating the
equations of motion uh of the classical
system the way averages tend to evolve
in time as I said under suitable
circumstances follows equations which
look very very much like the
corresponding classical equations all
right so our next goal is to try to
find the
rules for the time evolution of these
average values expectation values and
that's not so hard we have it we have
all the equipment we need to do
that and let's see if we can do
it all right so at any given time at any
given time the average of lambda is
given by s of t that's the state vector
at time
t the operator l representing the
observable times s of
t in other words I've just plugged in
for
a the actual time dependent state of the
system this is the average of l as a
function of time
i don't know what should we call it but
let's call it
uh okay it's the average of L as a
function of time again this is a kind of
a wrong notation it's not the average of
L of T it's the average of L as a
function of time
we could
uh we could put the T outside the
bracket
that's non-standard
subt but why don't we just go with
standard notation standard notation and
And
remember well okay I I'm not going to do
it i'm going to just call it average of
L as a function of time okay as a
function of time it is a function of
time that's the main thing it's a
function of time you could do something
else we could call it Lbar another
notation for average is to put a bar on
top of something that's another notation
for average standard notation and we
could just call it LB bar of t means the
average as a function of time let's
let's do it that way what would we like
to do with this we'd like to find
equations of motion for it in other
words we'd like to find out how it
changes with time by differentiating it
with respect to
time i want to take this quantity and
differentiate it with respect to time
so let's call it L dot now we have bars
with dots on top of
them l dot of T is the time derivative
of this now L of T that's just some
fixed operator it's some fixed definite
operator all of the time dependence is
in the state vectors the state vectors
change with time the
operators those are fixed those are
definite operators so let's see if we
can take the time derivative of this
here
thing the time derivatives act on the s
of t's when you take the time derivative
of a product and this can be a product
of vectors it can be a product of
numbers it can be a product of functions
well functions
uh the rule is always the same it's the
time derivative of one times the other
plus the time derivative of the other
times the one
that's very general so this is going to
equal then d si by dt the bra
vector l
si
plus s
l
dt oops I erased a very important
equation or else I buried it under the
uh under the
um blackboard let me write it over
here
dt is equal to minus
ih
s that's what we're going to stick in
over here so we we begin to see that the
Hamiltonian is going to tell us
something about how average values
change with time the Hamiltonian of
classical physics tells us how the
corresponding quantities change with
time the Hamiltonian of quantum
mechanics would tell us how the averages
change with time right we're going to
also need the bra version of this so
let's write the bra version of this the
bra version of it is d by dt of the bra
vector s of
t is
equal plus i
uh plus
i si
h h is hermission and so we don't have
to hermission conjugate it it is her
mission but we do have to change the
sign of I when we go from bras to
cats okay so now we're just going to
plug in let's just plug in and we'll get
L
dot yeah right l dot okay let's do this
one first over here this one is going to
be plus s and there's a minus sign minus
sign from here minus
I
s
L
H S
S that's what we get from here how about
the other one the other one is plus
I times the expectation value we have S
here S here we have S here S here i * H
L -
LH
S how about HL minus LH is that
zero why not HL who cares which way we
order through
well operators don't necessarily commute
commute means that you
can freely interchange the order of them
in general this is true of matrices
products of matrices don't necessarily
commute sometimes they do and in
particular an operator commutes with
itself l* L - L * L that That's okay you
can do it there l * L - L * L is zero
okay so is H * H - H * H but in
general L * H is not equal to H * L it
may be but typically
not what is this animal called h * L
minus L *
H it's called the commutator of the two
okay so this is a definition given two
operators
let's well they could be just H and L
the
combination HL minus
LH is written with a square
bracket H comma
L and it's called the
commutator commuting has something to do
with passing uh freely between each
other exactly what it has to do with
taking the subway in New York i don't
know people but
uh
uh but it's called the
commutator and so what we have here is
the equation that the
average of L at any given
time sorry the average of the time d the
time derivative of the average is equal
to
s comma theta h
l s but this object over here is just
the expectation value of commutator of h
with l so we can think of this as an
equation relating the time derivative of
a certain average to the average of
another quantity
we could I did I did is it plus it's
plus I I did
I or we can write L do of T is equal to
I well
average times average of the commutator
HL L and I'll indicate that by a bar on
top of it so we have equations of motion
now for averages in terms of
averages if the probability
distributions for everything are nice
and
peaked then we really can just say
approximately nice and peaked so that
the averages are close to to the to the
highest point on the curve and the curve
is reasonably narrow so there isn't an
enormous amount of
uncertainty then this basically says
that the time derivative
of the classical or the time derivative
of the approximate L of T is equal to
the approximate average of commutator of
H with L and someone writes this of
course is not quite right but right
anyway L dot is equal to I * commutator
HL now as I said this has to be taken
with a little grain of salt
uh what it means is an equation among
averages means an equation among
averages but it's often just written in
this form l dot is equal to h *
l okay okay now before we finish I want
to remind you of a classical mechanics
equation of
motion it's the equations of motion
represented did in terms of posome
brackets do you remember pone brackets
good old pone brackets fish
brackets what were the pone equations of
motion anybody
remember and if
you
right right d by dt exactly d by dt of a
classical function and this could be a
classical function of q's and p's in
classical mechanics we have q's and
p's l incidentally is a standard
notation for angular momentum this could
be the angular momentum but uh right now
I'm just using it to represent any
observable uh d by dt of l is equal
to a certain par bracket and the parome
bracket is the pos
bracket of
l with the hamiltonian
remember
that probably some of you don't but I'll
advise you to go and look it up it's in
the last It's in
the next to
last lecture of a classical mechanics uh
on plus
brackets uh and I will not go through it
here i just wanted to remind you of it
and I want you to notice the similarity
where is it did we did we erase it i
think I erased it the similarity of this
with DL by
DT average value is I minus I or plus I
I lost back plus I
I times the
commutator of H with L now incidentally
okay let's let's just point out one
thing plus brackets have the property
that if you interchange the two
expressions what happens to the plusone
bracket it just changes
sign so do commutators hl minus lh if
you interchange the order of them change
sign so we can also write this as
minus L with H commutator of L with
H there's a remarkable similarity and it
suggests
that we
identify the plusone
bracket
with minus I times the
commutator now I've left out a
discussion of something i just realized
it just now and I've completely
forgotten about it what happened to H
bar what happened to H
bar we've been working in units in which
H bar is
one i've been working in units in which
H bar plunk's constant is one the
question is if we were to reinstate
Plunk's constant and make it not equal
to one where would it go in these
equations and what's that
yes it goes in Schroinger's equation
that's correct but how do how do how do
we trace it let's see how do we trace it
here is the equation here i told you
that H has the significance of a
Hamiltonian and therefore it has units
of
energy so let's look at this equation
the S cancels out on both sides as far
as units go the units of this S are the
same as the units of this S and so the
right hand side of the equation apart
from the size has units of an energy the
left hand side of the equation has units
of inverse
time inverse time and energy don't have
the same
units inverse time is inverse seconds
and energy is jewels or whatever so we
have an equation here which doesn't make
good dimensional sense
we need a constant in
here and the constant we have to put a
constant in here uh let's see where does
a constant go does it go on the right
hand side or the left hand
side where does Plunk's constant go
right hand side or left hand side either
what either
if it goes in one place in one thing
then it goes in the inverse in the other
place okay
so here's all you have to know is that
plunk's constant has units of energy
times time plunk's constant has units of
energy times time uh so let's see so
energy times time so we want to put
plunks constant here energy times time
over time is equal to energy that's
where plunk's constant goes into these
equations uh and I apologize for having
completely forgotten about it
but that's where it
goes
and if we follow it through the
equations no doubt it appears over here
uh I think it appears in the denominator
here yeah you see I got everything right
except where I have h I should have h
over h
bar right we could rewrite this this way
h over H bar so in all of my equations
wherever we wrote H the Hamiltonian we
really should have if we want to keep
the units straight H over plunks
constant and that goes straight through
to here so really the right equation
including the constants is the
LDT is one is one over H bar
here 1 over plunk's
constant plunk's constant is a small
number so this looks like it's very big
but on the other hand this is L * H - H
* L in classical physics that would be
zero so whatever this
is classicalally it's zero and quantum
mechanically it must be a small
correction to the classical physics to
the extent that quantum mechanics is a
small correction to classical physics
and so the commutator is itself
something which is typically small and
of order h bar so that allows us then to
guess to guess an
identification between commutators and
plus brackets
now
I'm this this is non-intuitive at the
moment it's just a uh just looking at
two equations and saying look if there's
going to be any connection between
quantum mechanics and classical
mechanics then there must be a
connection between the plusone bracket
and between the plusone bracket and the
commutator namely plus bracket must be
equal to minus i
over h
har time
commutator or it's usually written
written the other way commutator is I H
bar times plus ohm
bracket commutator is a small thing
because there's an h bar there plus oh
bracket in classical physics is not a
small thing it's some number i mean it's
some characteristic quantity which is
not neither small nor big and in the
same units the units that you do
classical physics the standard units
meters seconds whatever commutators are
very small that's because they're almost
zero a * B minus B * A is almost zero
okay i No I don't think so i think I uh
we had a minus I on this side minus I
over H bar multiply by H bar
and now multiply both sides by i and use
that minus i * plus i is
one
yeah right it was dra who recognized
this connection and built his quantum
mechanics out of it he built his quantum
mechanics out of um making an
identification of plusone brackets with
with uh with commutators but of course
the foundations of the subject um
quantum mechanics is a consistent
subject without having to make any
reference to classical physics the right
way to think about things is that
quantum mechanics comes before classical
mechanics commutate is before plus own
brackets you have to derive classical
physics as an approximation to uh to
quantum mechanics so here we see some
formal similarity at this point here we
have no idea why this commutator should
have features in common with a plus
bracket before we go let me just say
let's let me write down some of the
features of commutators and plus
brackets to remind
you
uh and again all of this should be at
this stage should be a little mysterious
what what is this funny connection
between pos brackets but uh but uh let's
pursue it anyway okay let me remind you
about uh about posome brackets first of
all if I have two
quantities I'll call them A and B now or
maybe A and B I use
for let's just call them L and H they
don't have to be the Hamiltonian and
anything special they're just L and H
all right the first thing is the plusone
bracket of L with H is equal to minus
the plusone bracket of H with
L okay the commutator of L with
H is minus the commutator of H with
L so that's a parallelism that we can
begin with now let's take some other uh
let's take some other properties of
plusone
brackets um there's a lot of properties
of plusone brackets but let me just uh
write one or two more
if I
have two operators or two not operators
but two quantities let's call them L and
M okay L time M is itself a classical
quantity and I can compute its poson
bracket with H does anybody remember the
answer i'll remind you i'll tell you go
look it up get the this is um
important it's L it's a plus bracket of
L with
H time
M
plus L times a plus bracket of M with
H now in classical physics the order of
multiplication doesn't
matter so you can bring the m on the
left or the right it doesn't matter you
can bring the L on the left or right it
doesn't matter but this is the
relationship for the product of two
variables the plusone bracket go back go
back to the next to the last lecture and
uh check this out this was one of the
defining not one of the defining one of
the properties of home brackets you can
do the same you can ask the same
question over here supposing you have L
M and you take its commutator with
H what do you get all right this is an
exercise this is an exercise and all you
do is you write that this is equal to L
MH minus H
LM and now you start just juggling and
uh adding some terms subtracting the
same terms and eventually you'll
discover that this is the same as this
same relationship that this is equal
to L times the commutator of M with
H plus
uh commutator of L with
H time M
the way to do this is just write L MH
minus HLM and then write out these guys
here this is L MH minus
LHM plus
LHM minus
HLM four terms here two will cancel in
pairs and you'll just get this back it's
it's it's a onestep thing it's a really
easy thing okay so you you begin to see
some pattern that plus brackets and uh
and commutators must somehow be closely
related the
last thing I'm going to show you tonight
is about energy
conservation now we're not going to to
to consider the most general concept of
energy conservation we're simply going
to ask is the average of the energy
conserved with
time we have not even really gotten to
what it would mean for energy itself to
be conserved in any deeper way but we
can ask we have all the ingredients now
which will allow us to ask how the
average
of here's how an average of any quantity
changes with time no here it is over
here we can now specifically ask how the
average of the energy changes with time
let's do it
the energy I claim is the Hamiltonian
okay or its definition if you like what
is energy it's Hamiltonian so let's
check and ask whether energy is
conserved if energy is the Hamiltonian
this equation would
read the time derivative of the average
of the
Hamiltonian is equal the minus i over h
bar
times the commutator of the Hamiltonian
with
itself the Hamiltonian with itself it's
H * H minus H * H h * H is the same as H
* H well quantum mechanics is not that
weird you know it's weird but h* h is
the same as h time h so this is
zero whatever the Hamiltonian is its
average its average its expectation
value with time is always
zero and so it's conserved in that sense
at minimum in that sense there's a
stronger sense in which it's conserved
and we'll come to it
but even this weaker sense is kind of
interesting and it tells us we're on
some kind of right track to be able to
compare quantum mechanics and classical
mechanics okay uh I'm gonna stop now and
take a few questions and yeah um
here
[Music]
probably i just mean the average i mean
the average defined
uh defined as summation of probability
of lambda times
lambda okay so um I don't know what's
the standard symbol in statistics for an
average in the sense
they use they do what first moment of
the distribution
the first moment of the distribution
yeah okay
yeah yeah okay so
um I'm used to just calling it
lambda brackets e brackets of lambda e
bracket of lambda and that stands for
what the the average expected value
expected value even though it's not the
expected value you don't expect to get
it yeah yeah okay
um you've never seen the expect the
average value of a bar on top of it yeah
yeah i mean it's normal convention is
that it means the sample mean like the
average in okay yeah when I use the term
average I will mean this it's also
called the expectation value and I will
freely interchange the drack notation
for the average
with the bar notation
okay and if that's not uh if that's not
standard according to um statistics
books too bad
um so over here you wrote down the
Schroinger equation yes and then you
wrote down uh the
uh how did you go from the left hand
equation to the right hand equation was
that complex conjugation or was that
hermission conjugation hermission
conjugation
but remember that H is her mission we
proved that that
was that was the condition of unitarity
that H is her mission but how come you
you you interchange the order of SI and
H but not DDT and where where where
on on the left side equation you got DDT
s
ddt is the operator this one here yeah
yeah the time derivative of a bra vector
is a bra vector the time derivative of a
k look the time derivative is just
another way of talking about differences
the difference of two bra vectors is a
bra vector the difference of two k
vectors is a k vector okay in the limit
the difference becomes the time
derivative or the derivative so the
derivative of a bra vector is a bra
vector the derivative of a k vector is a
k vector if you want to take this K
equation what is the bra that goes with
this K the bra that's dual to this K is
the time derivative of the corresponding
bra vector so since time's not an
operator you don't have to worry right
time time is just think of this as
taking the difference of two vectors
yeah it's just a difference of two
vectors uh
right exactly
and
uh again quantum mechanics is weird but
uh taking the difference of two vectors
and replacing it by a derivative when
the difference is small uh that's
perfectly legitimate
you said that the form of Hamiltonian we
will choose depending on symmetry
considerations
well yeah in in in the derivation here
we did not put any symmetry
consideration so far no so why is it
then that we are getting energy
conservation out how come we're getting
what energy conservation out how do we
know that it's corresponding to energy
well we don't know that it's
corresponding to energy until we do a
lot more we don't know that we can
define it to be energy the Hamiltonian
but that's not satisfying we want to see
in cases where we understand the
classical
physics and we understand what energy is
we're going to want to see that the
quantum mechanics of the same system the
classical system is an approximation to
the quantum mechanical system physics is
really quantum mechanical under certain
conditions such as a system is heavy uh
basically that that it's heavy that it's
big that it uh uh large masses then the
system behaves approximately classically
which means that the average values move
in ways which are consistent with the
classical equations of motion we're
going to want to see that when uh that
when we study such big heavy systems
that uh that the thing that we call the
quantum mechanical
Hamiltonian is essentially closely
connected with the thing that we call
the classical Hamiltonian but we'll come
to that we can't do everything all in
one night at the moment I'm just s
showing you similarities and uh we're
going to want to do better than that
whether we'll actually get to do better
than that I don't know we can't do
everything but
[Music]
uh that's the logic yeah
i'm getting way back to the electron
spin i I think when we left off the last
lecture you were going to show what the
probability is to off yeah uh right i
had saved some time to do that but I run
Well I think I've done enough for
tonight um who was it who sent in the
solution to it uh
Yeah yeah well
done right so uh but we'll we'll do it
we'll do it i I just I've run out of
steam
um right we'll come back to that we're
going to come back to that um so how can
your postulates work without a collapse
postulate what's that how can your
postulates work without a collapse
postulate well we really want we really
want to derive the collapse postulate
but the derivation is deeply connected
with something else that we haven't come
to yet and I think we're going to come
to it next time
entanglement
uh the measurement process is really a
process of establishing entanglement
between a system and an apparatus
and until we've talked about um the
entanglement process I think uh until we
do we uh simply have
to adopt the language of collapse but uh
next time next time next time remind me
about collapse i'm close to collapse
so okay
for more please visit us at stanford.edu